The present is what it is
because of Ougi Oshino.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
忍野扇がいてくれたから 今がある
Because that mysterious girl, as if an
unknown was wrapped with unknowns,
謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, くるむ:to wrap up/to tuck in/to pack
あの謎めいた 正体不明を正体不明でくるんだような彼女が
was here in our town,
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
僕達の町にいてくれたからこそ
I, and all of us, were able to arrive
where we are now.
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 辿り着く[たどりつく]:to arrive at (after a struggle)/to finally reach/to find one's way to
僕は そして僕達は 今に辿り着けた
We have the present, and
we have a future.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
今があり 先がある
Someday the day will come
when I can feel that way.
風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
そんな風に思えるときが いつかきっと来るのだろう
That's just who I am.
僕はそういう奴で
And that's just who she is.
彼女はそういう者だ
Ougi Oshino.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
忍野扇
She was a symbol of my adolescence
-- that is how I remember her.
青春[せいしゅん]:youth/springtime of life/adolescent, 象徴[しょうちょう]:symbol, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
彼女は僕の青春の象徴だと
僕は彼女を思い出す
That smirking smile of hers.
にやにや:grinning/smirking, 笑顔[えがお]:smiling face/smile
にやにやとした彼女の笑顔
I'm sure that to her, my stupidity
was something she found highly amusing.
愚かしい[おろかしい]:foolish/stupid, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, 違い[ちがい]:difference/discrepancy
彼女にとっては 僕の愚かしさが面白かったに違いないのだ
I find myself laughing as well.
自身[じしん]:by oneself/personally, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
僕自身 笑ってしまう
Koyomi Araragi
I burst into laughter.
大笑い[おおわらい]:great laughter/burst of laughter, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
大笑いしてしまう
So in the end, maybe this
whole thing was just a comedy.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 笑い話[わらいばなし]:funny story, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ならば結局 笑い話だったのかもしれない
2                                                                                                3
My youth,
過ごす[すごす]:to pass (time)|to overdo (esp. of one's alcohol consumption)|to take care of||, 青春[せいしゅん]:youth/springtime of life/adolescent
僕が過ごした青春は
The last year I spent as
a high school student...
過ごす[すごす]:to pass (time)|to overdo (esp. of one's alcohol consumption)|to take care of||, 高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of)
僕が過ごした高校生活最後の一年間は
It was painful, it was sad,
辛い[からい]:spicy|salty|harsh (criticism)|, 辛い[つらい]:painful|tough|cruel, 悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful
辛くもあり 悲しくもあり
it was bitter, it was ugly,
and all in all, it was a hell of a year.
苦い[にがい]:bitter, 醜い[みにくい]:ugly/unattractive|unsightly, しよう:way/method|(technical) specification, しよう:use/application/employment, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of)
苦くもあり 醜くもあり どうしようもなくもあった一年間は
Thursday, March 15th
But even so, when I look
back on this someday,
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
それでも いつか思い出すとき
when I tell someone, or
everyone, about this...
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
誰かに話すとき 皆に伝えるとき
I know that maybe I should tell it with
a smile, like it was a simple, happy story
語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate, 笑顔[えがお]:smiling face/smile, 他愛[たあい]:altruism, 自愛[じあい]:taking care of oneself (esp. used as an epistolary imperative)|self-love, 満ちる[みちる]:to be full|to wax (e.g. moon)|to rise (e.g. tide)|
語るときは 笑顔で語るべき
他愛のない自愛に満ちた
that makes everyone who hears it laugh.
笑い話[わらいばなし]:funny story, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
笑い話だったのかもしれない
You "maybe" know? No, you know.
I don't know anything, though.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, いいえ:no/nay|well
しれない? いいえ 知っているはずですよ
私は何も知りませんが
I'm sure this is what Ougi-chan would say.
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
扇ちゃんなら きっとこう言う
You know, Araragi-senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
あなたが知っているんです 阿良々木先輩
That's right. I had known.
そう 僕は知っていた
Naoetsu High
I'm sure I knew exactly what Ougi
Oshino was from the very beginning.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 尽くす[つくす]:to exhaust|to devote|to do to exhaustion
忍野扇の正体も 最初からきっと
知り尽くしていたのだ
Naoetsu High School
And it's hilarious.
笑える[わらえる]:to be made to laugh
笑えることに
Ougi Dark
Part One
Shirohebi Park
Hey, hey! The pitcher is
getting spooked!
ピッチャー:pitcher, ビビる:to feel nervous|to be startled|to be shy
へいへーい ピッチャービビってますよー
She was wearing a skirt,
but crouching down and opening her legs like a catcher,
so you could see her panties easily.
She was really letting her guard down,
but honestly, I didn't want to see them anyway.
A rock?
They're throwing rocks and
batting with swords...
What kind of baseball is this?
No.
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目
You're going to settle
the score tonight, right?
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight
ケリつけるんでしょ 今夜で
Well, yeah, but...
まあ そうだけど...
Now that Big Sister isn't here,
I can't be of any help to you...
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
お姉ちゃんがいない今 僕は何の力にもなれないけれど
But at the least, I can watch you fight
with my own eyes, Big Demo-ther.
鬼[おに, き]:oni|spirit of a deceased person|ogre-like person (i.e. fierce, relentless, merciless, etc.)||, 戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle, 見届ける[みとどける]:to make sure of/to assure oneself of/to see with one's own eyes, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
鬼いちゃんの戦いを見届けるくらいのことはしてあげるよ
So... let's hurry up and join that circle.
輪[りん]:counter for wheels and flowers, 輪[わ]:ring|hoop|wheel|
だから さっさとあの輪に入ろう
Oh, if it isn't you, my master!
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, あるじ:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest
おお! お前様ではないか! 我があるじ様!
H-Hachikuji...
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
は 八九寺...
No, you did plenty of that back in hell.
Haven't you had enough, Baragaki-san?
地獄[じごく]:hell, 散々[さんざん]:thoroughly|severely|scattered
いや それはもう地獄で散々やったからいいじゃないですか
バラガキさん
Well, that sounds really cool, but Hachikuji,
格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
いや 格好いいけれども 八九寺
don't refer to me as if I was
Toshizo Hijikata in his youth.
土方[どかた, つちかた]:construction worker/laborer (labourer)/navvy, 少年[しょうねん]:boy/juvenile/young boy, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
人を土方(ひじかた)歳三(としぞう)の少年時代みたいに言わないでもらおうか
My name is Araragi.
僕の名前は阿良々木だ
I'm sorry, I flubbed (kami-mashita).
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|, 噛む[かむ]:to bite|to crash against (e.g. of waves)|to engage (of cogs, zippers, etc.)||, 噛む[しがむ]:to chew (strongly)
失礼 噛みました
No, that was intentional.
わざと:on purpose
違う わざとだ...
I fwubbed.
かみまみた
It's not intentional?
わざと:on purpose
わざとじゃない!?
I crouched.
屈む[かがむ, こごむ]:to stoop/to lean over/to bend down
屈(かが)みました
You were indeed sitting
catcher-style there, but...
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, キャッチャー:catcher, スタイル:figure/body build
確かにキャッチャースタイルだったけれど!
It's good to see you too, Ononoki-san.
Thank you for your help earlier.
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you), 節[せつ]:occasion|section (of a literary work)|principle||, 節[のっと, ノット]:knot (nautical mile per hour), お世話になる[おせわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted
斧乃木さんもお久しぶりです その節はお世話になりました
Yup. I feel happy about your return.
帰還[きかん]:repatriation/return|(electrical) feedback, 嬉しい[うれしい]:happy/glad/pleasant
うむ きみの帰還を嬉しく思うよ
There was a matter that I
should have checked up on.
What's wrong, Hachikuji?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
どうした八九寺
No, what's wrong with your brain?
脳[のう]:brain|brains/mind, 脳[なずき]:brain/skull/head
あなたの脳こそどうしましたか
Why did you so suddenly attempt to
clutch my growing breasts?
おもむろに:suddenly/abruptly|deliberately, わたし:I/me|private affairs, わたし:ferry (crossing)/ferry(boat)|delivery, 成長[せいちょう]:growth/grow to adulthood, 過程[かてい]:process/course/mechanism, 乳房[ちぶさ, にゅうぼう]:breast/nipple/udder, わしづかみ:grabbing hold/eagle grip/tight hold, 試みる[こころみる]:to try/to attempt/to have a go (at something)
なぜおもむろに わたしの成長過程の乳房をわしづかみにしようと試みたのですか
Well, I was wondering what kind of
condition you were in right now.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, コンディション:condition
いや 今のお前って
どういうコンディションなんだろうと思って
She's a phantom, just like she was
when you first met her here in this park.
コンディション:condition, 公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 同様[どうよう]:identical/equal to/same (kind), 幽霊[ゆうれい]:ghost/specter/spectre, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
今の彼女のコンディションは
きみがこの公園で初めて会ったときと同様の 幽霊状態だよ
She's a ghost.
ゴースト:ghost
ゴーストだ
I'm sorry, Hachikuji. I wasn't
thinking when I brought you here.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
ごめん 八九寺
考えなしに連れて来ちゃったけれど
Come to think of it, I've made your labors piling
stones for the past six months all for naught.
半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 石[いし]:stone|gem/jewel, 石[こく]:measure of volume (approx. 180.39 liters, 6.37 cub. ft.)|measure of a Japanese-style boat's loading capacity (approx. 278.26 liters), 積む[つむ]:to pile up|to load (car, ship, etc.)|to acquire, 労働[ろうどう]:manual labor/manual labour|Labour Party, 無にする[むにする]:to bring to naught/to bring to nought/to waste
思えば僕は お前が半年間
石を積んでいた労働を無にしちゃったんだよな
It's fine, Araragi-san.
Don't worry about it.
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, なさる:to do, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
いいんですよ 阿良々木さん
お気になさらないでください
I've already settled things with
Gaen-san concerning that.
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 既に[すでに, すんでに]:already/too late, 話がつく[はなしがつく]:to come to an agreement
その辺については
既に臥煙さんと話がついていますので
Settled things?
話がつく[はなしがつく]:to come to an agreement
話がついている?
Well, we can discuss all that in
the briefing. Let's get started.
まあまあ:so-so|now, now (used in calming people down), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 含める[ふくめる]:to include (in a group or scope)|to instruct|to include (a nuance)||, ブリーフィング:briefing, 開始[かいし]:start/commencement/beginning
まあまあ そういう話も含めて
ブリーフィングを開始しようじゃないか
For the moment, Koyomin, can you give orders
to your now-mature, beautiful slave girl,
さしあたる:to face the situation, こよみ:calendar/almanac, 成長[せいちょう]:growth/grow to adulthood, 美女[びじょ]:beautiful woman, 奴隷[どれい]:slave/servant|slavery, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
さしあたってこよみん
成長したきみの美女奴隷に命令して
and have her stop bullying my
junior colleague shikigami?
後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 式神[しきがみ]:form of magic or divination (e.g. animating objects to act as the sorcerer's agent), いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
私の後輩の式神をいじめるのを止めさせてもらっていいだろうか
There, there, there!
オレ! オレ! オレ!
She seems to be doing what
Ononoki-chan feared.
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 恐れる[おそれる]:to fear/to be afraid of
斧乃木ちゃんが恐れていた
Getting revenge for all of the insults she
received back in the summer.
夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 浴びる[あびる]:to dash over oneself (e.g. water)/to take (e.g. shower)|to suffer (e.g. an attack), 数々[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数々[かずかず]:many/numerous/various, 暴言[ぼうげん, もうげん]:reckless remark/rash remark/abusive language, 仕返し[しかえし]:being even with/reprisal/tit for tat, 最中[さいちゅう, さなか]:in the middle of/height of/in course of, 最中[もなか]:wafer cake filled with bean jam, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
夏に浴びた数々の暴言の仕返しの最中らしい
Shinobu Oshino
The complete form of the legendary vampire
who flew in from overseas.
Mayoi Hachikuji
A ghost that returned from hell.
Yotsugi Ononoki
A shikigami corpse doll whose master has ran away.
Izuko Gaen
The leader of a group of specialists who defeat apparitions.
And me, Koyomi Araragi, once human,
previously vampire, and currently human.
Stop it, Hachikuji.
Don't look at me like that.
All right. It's time for your big sister
さて これからおねーさんが
to tell you about the plan she spent
the last few days working on.
昨日今日[きのうきょう]:yesterday and today|(something that happened) only yesterday (just recently), 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 立てる[たてる]:to stand up|to thrust into|to make (a noise)||, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 開示[かいじ]:release (e.g. information)/disclosure (legal)/show
昨日今日で頑張って立てた計画をきみ達に開示する
Koyomin, did you bring it as I asked?
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
こよみん 言ったものは持ってきてくれたかな?
I did bring it.
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
持ってはきました
But this belonged to you in the first place,
Gaen-san, so I wanted to return it to you.
元々[もともと]:originally/by nature/from the start, 持ち物[もちもの]:one's property/personal effects/one's belongings, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
ですけれど 元々 "あれ" は臥煙さんの持ち物だったから
返すために持ってきたのであって
Mm, indeed. It has been preserved well.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 保存[ほぞん]:preservation/conservation|saving (e.g. to disk), 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
うん 確かに いい保存状態だね
It looks like you took
very good care of it.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
大事にしてくれていたみたいじゃあないか
Ougi Oshino.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
忍野扇
That is the enemy who we are
going to face right now.
私達[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 向かい合う[むかいあう]:to be opposite/to face each other, 敵[かたき]:rival|revenge|spouse, 敵[てき]:opponent/rival|menace
それが私達が 今から向かい合う "敵" だ
The opponent we must fight, the target we
must eliminate, and the focus of our hatred.
戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 憎む[にくむ]:to hate/to detest
戦うべき相手だ
退治すべき対象で 憎むべき対象だ
Isn't that right, Koyomin?
こよみ:calendar/almanac
そうだよね? こよみん
Naturally, this is the
most important point.
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 重要[じゅうよう]:important/momentous/essential, ポイント:point
もっとも ここが重要なポイントだけれども
The name "Ougi Oshino" was merely used
as a convenience. Don't forget that.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, あくまで:to the end/to the bitter end|after all, 便宜上[べんぎじょう]:for convenience/as a matter of convenience, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
忍野扇という名前は
あくまでも便宜(べんぎ)上のものであることを忘れてはならない
The true nature of Ougi Oshino is unknown.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 本質[ほんしつ]:essence/true nature/substance, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
忍野扇の本質は 正体不明にこそあるからね
The loss of her true identity is the
only identity she has.
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 唯一[ゆいいつ, ゆいつ]:only/sole/unique, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
正体を失うことこそが
彼女の持つ唯一の彼女らしさなのだから
First, let's go over it step-by-step.
順を追う[じゅんをおう]:to follow in order/to go through step-by-step
まずは順を追っていこうか
We don't have time, and I'll only
explain once, so listen up.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
時間もないし 一度しか説明しないから よく聞いてね
Notes
There's one thing I want to confirm.
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ひとつ 確認しておきたいんですけれど
Are you sure that Ougi-chan will
be on the move sometime tonight?
扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 確信[かくしん]:conviction/belief/confidence
扇ちゃんが今夜中に動くっていうのは
確信があるんですか?
She will. I'm not simply "sure."
That's just the reality of it.
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 確信[かくしん]:conviction/belief/confidence, 事実[じじつ]:fact/truth/reality
動くね それは確信があるというよりは ただの事実だ
She only has tonight. If she doesn't act tonight,
that would imply that it's not actually her.
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, むしろ:rather/better/instead, むしろ:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
今夜しかない ここで動かないなら
むしろ彼女じゃないと言える
And thus, there is no threat at all.
脅威[きょうい]:threat/menace, 消滅[しょうめつ]:extinction/extinguishment|annihilation
脅威は消滅するともね
Well, for this case, I did toss out the
question, but I was pretty convinced, too.
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, 確信[かくしん]:conviction/belief/confidence
あ この件に関しては 僕にも確信があった
Because she said so herself.
本人[ほんにん]:the person himself
だって 本人がそう言っていたのだから
Araragi-senpai, could you be on my side?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter
阿良々木先輩 私の味方をしてくれませんか?
Please, help me.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
私を助けてください
We'll start by talking
about the relationship
公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate
じゃあまずは この公園と
北白蛇神社の関係からでも 語るとするかな
between this park and
North Shirahebi Shrine.
From the source that leads
up to the current tragedy.
悲劇[ひげき]:tragedy/tragic drama|tragedy, 到る[いたる]:to arrive at (e.g. a decision)|to lead to (a place)|to come, 濫觴[らんしょう]:source/beginning/origin
今の悲劇に到る濫觴(らんしょう)から
From the tragedy 400 years ago
that fell upon Shirohebi Shrine,
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 前身[ぜんしん]:antecedents/ancestor/previous position, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit
北白蛇神社の前身 沱白神社を襲った
the previous incarnation of
North Shirahebi Shrine.
悲劇[ひげき]:tragedy/tragic drama|tragedy
四百年前の悲劇から
Now, what exactly happened 400 years ago?
四百年前 と言えば 何があっただろう?
Right. The legendary vampire, Kiss-shot
Acerola-orion Heart-under-blade visited Japan.
伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 訪日[ほうにち]:visit to Japan
そう 伝説の吸血鬼
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードの訪日だ
着地[ちゃくち]:landing
その時の着地によって
Now, when she landed,
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 国[くに]:country|region|national government||, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 地方[ちほう]:district/region|the country, 地方[じかた]:person in charge of music (in a Japanese dance performance)|person singing ballads (in noh)|coast (esp. as seen from the water)|, 溜まる[たまる]:to collect/to gather/to save
そこにあった 日本という国の
一地方に溜まっていた水を
all the water that had built up in a
lake in that particular area of Japan
湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 散らす[ちらす]:to scatter|to disperse|to resolve (a symptom, condition, etc.)||
湖を散らした
was dispersed.
She scattered it.
蹴散らす[けちらす]:to kick about/to kick around|to scatter (e.g. one's enemies)
蹴散らした
That lake was no ordinary lake.
湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names)
その湖が ただの湖ではなかった
It was a sacred lake that was the
focus of worship for the whole region.
地方[ちほう]:district/region|the country, 地方[じかた]:person in charge of music (in a Japanese dance performance)|person singing ballads (in noh)|coast (esp. as seen from the water)|, 信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 一身[いちみ]:partisans/gang/conspirators, 一身[いっしん]:oneself/one's own interests/throughout the body, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 神聖[しんせい]:holiness/sacredness/sanctity, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names)
その地方の信仰を一身に集めていた
神聖なる湖だった
But this blasphemous deed of hers
proved to be to the region's benefit.
杯盤[はいばん]:glasses and plates, 狼藉[ろうぜき]:violence/outrage/riot, 地域[ちいき]:area/region, 恩恵[おんけい]:grace/favor/favour, 与える[あたえる]:to give (esp. to someone of lower status)|to provide|to assign||
しかしこの杯盤狼藉は
地域に恩恵も与えたのだよ
Because the water from the lake that
flew up from the impact of landing...
着弾[ちゃくだん]:impact (of a projectile), 衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 舞い上がる[まいあがる]:to soar/to fly high|to make merry, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names)
着弾の衝撃で舞い上がった 湖の水は
...fell back down onto the area,
当時[とうじ]:at that time/in those days, 旱魃[かんばつ]:drought/long spell (period) of dry weather, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 現地[げんち]:actual place/local/on-site, 降る[くだる]:to descend|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.)|to pass (of time)||, 降る[ふる]:to precipitate/to fall (e.g. rain), 恵み[めぐみ]:blessing/grace, 雨[あめ]:rain
そのまま 当時 旱魃(かんばつ)状態にあった現地に降る
恵みの雨となったのだから
which was suffering from a drought
at the time, as blessed rain.
As a result, the Western apparition
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 西洋[せいよう]:the west/Western countries, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker
結果 西洋の怪異である吸血鬼
Kiss-shot Acerola-orion Heart-under-blade,
a vampire, took over the local religion.
アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 現地[げんち]:actual place/local/on-site, 信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.), ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードは
現地の信仰を乗っ取ることになった
You could say that she defeated the
previous god and took over its position.
蹴散らす[けちらす]:to kick about/to kick around|to scatter (e.g. one's enemies), 立場[たちば]:standpoint/position/situation, 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.)
言うなら神を蹴散らし 神の立場を乗っ取った
With no more lake, and no more god to
worship, they had to find a new god.
信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
信仰すべき湖を失い 神を失った彼らは
新たなる神を見つけなくてはならなかった
No, they had to create a new god.
否[ひ]:no/the noes, 否[いいえ, いいや]:no|well|you're welcome, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
否 新たなる神を作らなくてはならなかった
That is why they relocated the shrine.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 移築[いちく]:dismantling an historic building and reconstructing it elsewhere
そのために 神社を移築した
The locals, who'd lost both their
faith and much of their numbers,
信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 人口[じんこう]:population|common talk, 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 現地[げんち]:actual place/local/on-site, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
どうやら 信仰も人口も失った現地の皆さんは
decided to try and survive by
merging with a local folk religion.
近場[ちかば]:nearby place, 土着[どちゃく]:aboriginal/indigenous, 信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 合流[ごうりゅう]:confluence (of rivers)/merge (of traffic)|union (e.g. of forces), 生き延びる[いきのびる]:to survive/to live long, 道を探る[みちをさぐる]:to seek a path/to find one's way
近場の土着信仰と合流することで
生き延びる道を探ったようだね
And this wasn't necessarily a bad decision.
まるっきり:completely/perfectly/totally, 的外れ[まとはずれ]:off the mark/off base/misdirected
それは まるっきり的外れだったというわけでもない
There was a tie between these
two that enabled the grafting.
接ぎ木[つぎき]:grafting, 鎹[かすがい]:large staple driven into two pieces of wood to hold them together/clamp|tie (metaphorical, e.g. something that binds two people together)
接ぎ木をするための鎹(かすがい)はあったんだ
A tie, an axis... A cord that
connected the mountain and the lake.
鎹[かすがい]:large staple driven into two pieces of wood to hold them together/clamp|tie (metaphorical, e.g. something that binds two people together), 軸[じく]:axis|center|stalk|, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 繋ぐ[つなぐ]:to connect|to tie|to maintain||, 紐[ひも]:string/cord|man who is financially dependent on a woman (such as a gigolo or, in the case of a prostitute, a pimp)
鎹... 軸
山と湖を繋ぐ紐はあった
Though I guess I should call it
a rope (nawa), and not a cord.
紐[ひも]:string/cord|man who is financially dependent on a woman (such as a gigolo or, in the case of a prostitute, a pimp), 縄[なわ]:rope/cord|policeman's rope
それは紐ではなく 縄と言うべきかな
A kuchinawa—in other words, a snake.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake
クチナワ つまりは蛇だ
The god that was worshiped at the lake
湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 神体[しんたい]:shintai/object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a deity, typically housed in a shrine, 具体的[ぐたいてき]:concrete/tangible/definite, 姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||
湖で信仰されていた神の
その神体の具体的な姿は水蛇でね
took the physical form of a water snake.
And the object of worship for
the small indigenous faith
山間[さんかん]:among the mountains, 山間[やまあい, やまま]:valley/ravine/glen, 小さな[ちいさな]:small/little/tiny, 土着[どちゃく]:aboriginal/indigenous, 信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 神体[しんたい]:shintai/object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a deity, typically housed in a shrine, 姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake
そして山間部での小さな土着信仰における神体の姿は
山蛇だった
in the mountains was shaped
like a mountain snake.
A water snake and a mountain snake.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake
水蛇と山蛇
A snake connection.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 繋がり[つながり]:connection/link/relationship
蛇繋がり
But this grafting proved to
be just a bit too forced.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 理に適う[りにかなう]:to make sense, 接ぎ木[つぎき]:grafting
だった やっぱり無理があったんだよ
理に適(かな)わない接ぎ木には
It might have appeared successful,
一見[いっけん]:look|apparently|first meeting, 一見[いちげん]:first visit to inn, restaurant, etc. without an introduction, 成立[せいりつ]:coming into existence/arrangements|to come into existence, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, やはり:too/also|still, 歪[いびつ]:distorted|oval|round, wooden container for cooked rice|, 感[かん]:feeling/sensation|interjection, 否む[いなむ]:to refuse/to decline|to deny, 否む[いやむ]:to detest/to dislike
一見成立していても
やはり歪(いびつ)な感は否めない
but there was still this
sense that something was off.
And being "off," being unbalanced, in
that way, created a type of air pocket.
歪[いびつ]:distorted|oval|round, wooden container for cooked rice|, アンバランス:unbalanced/imbalance, 一種[いっしゅ, ひとくさ]:species/kind/variety, 生む[うむ]:to give birth/to bear (child)|to produce
その歪さは アンバランスさは
一種のエアスポットを生んだ
An air pocket that gathered bad things.
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather
"よくないもの" を集める エアスポットを
The site of the eradicated lake
is here, Shirohebi Park...
跡形[あとかた]:trace/vestige/evidence, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names), 昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 跡地[あとち]:former site (of something)/site (e.g. of a demolished building), 浪[なみ]:wave, 白[しろ]:white|innocence|blank space||, 白[しら]:white|unseasoned|very much||, 公園[こうえん]:(public) park
跡形もなくなった湖が昔あった跡地がこの浪白公園であって
...and the mountain shrine where the faith had been
transferred is North Shirahebi Shrine, you see.
信仰[しんこう]:(religious) faith/belief/creed, 移築[いちく]:dismantling an historic building and reconstructing it elsewhere, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake
信仰が移築された先の山の神社というのが
北白蛇神社だったというわけなんだよ
North Shirahebi Shrine
By the way,
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage)
ちなみに
Shirohebi Shrine, now "North Shirahebi Shrine,"
managed to survive in a much diminished state,
細々[こまごま]:minutely/in detail/with particular attention, 細々[ほそぼそ]:poor (living)|barely continuing|very narrow, しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 先細り[さきぼそり]:dwindling/declining|tapering (to a point), ながら:while/during|while, 継続[けいぞく]:continuation, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 改める[あらためる]:to change|to reform|to examine|, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake
細々と しかも先細りしながら継続していた沱白神社改め北白蛇神社は
until finally collapsing 15 years ago.
約[やく]:approximately|promise|shortening|, 滅ぶ[ほろぶ]:to be ruined/to go under/to perish
約十五年前に滅んだ
He—the first minion of Shinobu-san—
his ashes came back to his homeland,
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 里帰り[さとがえり]:returning home/visiting one's parents/new bride's first visit to parents, 遂げる[とげる]:to accomplish/to achieve|to arrive at (a certain outcome)
忍さんの第一の眷属である "彼" が
彼" の "灰" が里帰りを遂げ
and as a result, he ate the "bad things"
that had gathered within the shrine grounds,
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 境内[けいだい]:grounds (esp. of shrines and temples)/compound/churchyard, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 喰う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
結果神社の境内に集まっていた "よくないもの" を
神様ごと喰ってしまったからね
and the god itself.
Because of all that had gone on, after the
case of that minion had been resolved...
経緯[いきさつ, けいい]:details|longitude and latitude|warp and weft, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 片付く[かたづく]:to be put in order|to be disposed of|to be finished|
そういった経緯があったからこそ
眷属の彼の件が片付いたあと
I had planned to enshrine Shinobu-san as
the new deity of North Shirahebi Shrine.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|
私は忍さんを 北白蛇神社の新たなる神として
据えようと思っていたんだよね
If you had explained everything with
that reasoning from the beginning...
That's what I was going to say,
but even if she had taken
the time to explain it,
I doubt I ever would've thought about
using that talisman on Shinobu.
Koyomin, why don't we take a little break
and make it clear where we both stand?
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 一旦[いったん]:once|for a short time|one morning, 休憩[きゅうけい]:rest/break/recess, 挟む[はさむ]:to interpose/to hold between|to be on either side (e.g. road), 挟む[さしはさむ]:to insert|to interrupt|to harbor (e.g. doubts), 互い[たがい]:mutual/reciprocal, 意見[いけん]:opinion/view/comment, はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 表明[ひょうめい]:declaration/indication/representation
こよみん ここで一旦休憩を挟んで
お互いの意見をはっきり表明してみないかい?
Where we both stand?
表明[ひょうめい]:declaration/indication/representation, 互い[たがい]:mutual/reciprocal, 意見[いけん]:opinion/view/comment
表明? お互いの意見を?
What we want, if you prefer
to put it that way.
目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information)
目的と言ってもいいけれどね 目的意識と言っても
Or what, exactly, we think we're doing here.
私達[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least, 協定[きょうてい]:arrangement/pact/agreement, 結ぶ[むすぶ]:to tie|to bear (fruit)|to close (e.g. deal)||
私達は決して協定を結んでいるわけではない
We don't have any kind of alliance here.
起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||, ミラクル:miracle, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, こよみ:calendar/almanac, プラン:plan, 組み入れる[くみいれる]:to incorporate/to work into/to insert
私としては きみの起こすミラクルに期待して
こよみんをプランに組み入れたものの
I brought you here expecting one of the
miracles you pull off.
But I can't deny that it might
just bring forth another disaster.
更なる[さらなる]:even more/still more/further, 災厄[さいやく]:calamity/disaster/accident, 引き起こす[ひきおこす]:to cause/to induce|to pull upright, 危険性[きけんせい]:riskiness/danger, 否定[ひてい]:negation/denial|NOT operation
それが更なる災厄を引き起こす危険性も否定できない
For example, when I put you
in charge of Shinobu-san,
当時[とうじ]:at that time/in those days, こよみ:calendar/almanac, 委ねる[ゆだねる]:to entrust (a matter) to/to leave to|to abandon oneself to (e.g. pleasure)
忍さん 当時は忍ちゃんをどうするか
こよみんに委ねてみたら
or Shinobu-chan, as she was known back then,
I never thought that the end result
would be an unrelated middle school girl
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 無関係[むかんけい]:unrelated, 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 中学生[ちゅうがくせい]:junior high school student/middle school pupil, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 結末[けつまつ]:end/conclusion, 辿り着く[たどりつく]:to arrive at (after a struggle)/to finally reach/to find one's way to, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
まさか無関係の女子中学生が神様に祀り上げられるなんて
結末に辿り着いちゃったみたいにね
being enshrined as a god.
Yeah, you've kinda got me there.
音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
それを言われるとぐうの音も出ません
In other words, since she couldn't trust
me, she wanted to know what I was after...
What was inside my heart.
I'll tell you, then. My objective is...
目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
じゃあ言いますけれど... 僕の目的は
For now, I'd like to do something
about Hachikuji and Shinobu.
とりあえず:first of all/at once|for now, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
とりあえず... 八九寺と忍のことを
なんとかしたいと思っています
Especially Hachikuji, as she might be
swallowed up by the darkness at this rate.
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 呑む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||, かねる:to be unable to/to find difficult (unpleasant, awkward, painful) to do|to serve two or more functions or roles simultaneously
特に八九寺は このままだと "くらやみ" に呑まれかねない
Well, remember that I said I
had a plan for Hachikuji-chan.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 腹案[ふくあん]:one's plan
まあ 八九寺ちゃんのことについては
私に腹案があると言っただろう
So, next I'd like to hear your
worries about Shinobu-san.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
だから次は忍さんについての心配を聞こうかな
You want to do something about Shinobu-san?
Koyomin, specifically what do you mean by that?
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 具体的[ぐたいてき]:concrete/tangible/definite, どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
忍さんのことをなんとかしたいというのは
こよみん 具体的にはどういう意味だい?
So like, she's like this now...
だから... 今 こうして こうなって...
And of course, I'm concerned about how
Oshino and Kagenui-san's whereabouts are unknown.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 所在[しょざい]:whereabouts, 知れる[しれる]:to become known|to be known|to obviously not amount to much||, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 気にかかる[きにかかる]:to weigh on one's mind/to be worried about (something)
忍野や影縫さんの所在が知れないことも
もちろん 気にかかっていて
Of course, I think it would be good for
the town I live in to be peaceful.
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is, 住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait
そりゃあ 僕だって
自分の住む町が平和であればいいとは思いますが
But I'm not capable of really
thinking about things in that way.
目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim, 据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
ただ それを目的に据えられるほどの一人物では
僕はありませんよ
At most, I can think about the safety
of the people around me.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 精々[せいぜい]:at the most/at best/to the utmost, 身近[みぢか]:near oneself/close to one/familiar, 知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance, 進退[しんたい]:movement/course of action/advance or retreat, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
僕に考えられるのは 精々
身近な知り合いの進退くらいのものです
And that's what makes this dangerous for me.
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk
それが私にとっては危険だと言っている
But we can deal with that.
折り合い[おりあい]:agreement (e.g. business, dispute)/compromise|mutual relations (e.g. between parents and child, coworkers, etc.)
が それなら折り合いもつけられる
At least, this time around.
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately
少なくとも 今回はね
By that, you mean..
と 言うのは?
You're worried about the people
close to you, but not yourself.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 身近[みぢか]:near oneself/close to one/familiar, 人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, 結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
きみが気にしているのは 身近な人々と言えど
結局は他人のことばかりだということだ
Since your own safety isn't a concern,
we can come to an agreement.
身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, まったく:really/truly|indeed, 案ずる[あんずる]:to be anxious or concerned about|to investigate|to pat, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 折り合う[おりあう]:to compromise
きみが自分の身をまったく案じていない以上
今回は私と折り合える
What about you, Shinobu-san?
忍さんは?
What is your objective?
目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
きみの目的は?
Shinobu-san, what are you thinking about
right now? What do you want to do?
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
忍さん きみは今 何を考えている?
何をどうしたいと思う?
I merely obey my master's orders.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 主人[しゅじん]:head (of a household)|one's husband|(one's) employer|, 主人[あるじ]:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 従う[したがう]:to abide (by the rules)/to obey/to follow
儂は ご主人様に従うまでじゃ
If my master says he will assist you,
that's what I will do as well.
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, あるじ:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration
我があるじ様がうぬに協力するというのならそうするまでじゃし
And if my master decides to oppose you,
that's what I will do as well.
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, あるじ:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 対立[たいりつ]:confrontation/opposition/antagonism
我があるじ様がうぬと対立するというのならそうするまでじゃ
Specialist, if I could speak for myself,
my desire is, if at all possible...
専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), 儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 希望[きぼう]:hope/wish/aspiration
専門家 言わせてもらえるならば
儂の希望としては できることなら
...to be returned to the
form of a young girl.
幼女[ようじょ]:little girl, 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price), 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, じゃが:potato (Solanum tuberosum)
幼女に戻して欲しいもんなんじゃがの
Now that our stances are all clear,
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, スタンス:stance/attitude/standpoint, 出そろう[でそろう]:to appear all together/to be all present
では 全員のスタンスが出そろったところで
I'll explain what, exactly,
we're about to do.
具体的[ぐたいてき]:concrete/tangible/definite, 動き[うごき]:movement/move|trend, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
これからの具体的な動きの説明に入ろう
I will explain the minimum requirements for
fulfilling Koyomin's objectives, my objectives,
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
こよみんの目的と私の目的
それに忍さんの目的と八九寺ちゃんの目的を
Shinobu-san's objectives, and
Hachikuji-chan's objectives simultaneously.
同時[どうじ]:simultaneous/concurrent/same time, 果たす[はたす]:to accomplish/to achieve|to do ... completely, 最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|, 条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
同時に果たすための最低条件の説明だ
Minimum Requirements
There are two minimum requirements.
最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|, 条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two
最低条件は二つ
One is to enshrine a new deity
in North Shirahebi Shrine,
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|
ひとつは北白蛇神社に新たなる神を据えること
and the other is the
extermination of Ougi Oshino.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness
そしてもうひとつは 忍野扇の退治だ
Extermination
Gaen-san...
臥煙さん
If you're talking about turning
Shinobu into a god—
据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
忍を神に据えようって話だったら
That's what I had been planning on.
そのつもりだったんだけれどね
But since Koyomin brought Hachikuji-chan back
from hell, the situation has changed.
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
しかし こよみんが地獄から八九寺ちゃんを連れてきたことで
状況が変わった
In a way, a surrogate god that is
even more fitting than Shinobu-san...
意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 相応しい[ふさわしい]:appropriate/adequate/suitable, 代理[だいり]:representation/agency/proxy
ある意味では忍さん以上に相応しい神の代理が
No, the successor to a god has appeared.
否[ひ]:no/the noes, 否[いいえ, いいや]:no|well|you're welcome, 跡継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
否 神の跡継ぎが 現れたのだから
The successor to a god?
跡継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor
神の... 跡継ぎ?
It's Hachikuji-chan.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺ちゃんだよ
N-No, that's even worse!
I mean, Hachikuji is—
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
い いや! そ そんなの もっと駄目でしょう!
だって八九寺は
Hachikuji is?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺は?
Well, I suppose she's qualified.
資格[しかく]:qualifications/requirements/capabilities, れんが:brick, れんが:early Japanese poetry form/poetic dialogue
まあ 資格はあるのかもしれんがの
At the point where she returned from hell,
地獄[じごく]:hell, 復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion
地獄から復活してくるという時点で
that lost girl undoubtedly
performed a miracle.
迷子[まいご]:lost child/lost person/stray child, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, 奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel, 果たす[はたす]:to accomplish/to achieve|to do ... completely
その迷子娘は
文句なくひとつの奇跡を果たしておるわけじゃし
But if that's the case, the condition is
also met by me, or even by Ononoki-chan—
条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, あるいは:or/possibly, 斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 満たす[みたす]:to satisfy|to fill (e.g. a cup)|to reach (a certain number)
しかしそれなら そんな条件は僕だって
あるいは斧乃木ちゃんだって満たしているわけで
It's not the same. It's different.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
同じじゃないよ 違うよ
You all returned, but in different ways.
復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term
復活したと言っても条件が違う
違い[ちがい]:difference/discrepancy, 様になる[ようになる]:to reach the point that/to come to be that/to turn into, 様になる[さまになる, サマになる]:to become good-looking/to start looking appropriate (for something)
違いは ここで神様にならなければ
The difference is that if she doesn't
turn into a god right here,
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 呑む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
八九寺ちゃんは "くらやみ" に呑まれるということだ
Hachikuji-chan will be swallowed
up by the darkness.
In other words, there are three choices.
三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 択[たく]:counter for choices, options, etc.
つまり三択だよ
One, she goes back to hell again.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 地獄[じごく]:hell, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
① もう一度地獄に帰る
Two, she gets swallowed up
into the "darkness."
くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 呑む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
② "くらやみ" に呑まれる
Three, she becomes a god.
様になる[ようになる]:to reach the point that/to come to be that/to turn into, 様になる[さまになる, サマになる]:to become good-looking/to start looking appropriate (for something)
③ 神様になる だ
By becoming enshrined at
North Shirahebi Shrine,
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||
北白蛇神社に祀り上げられることで
Mayoi Hachikuji will be granted
an existence in this material world.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 現世[げんせい, げんせ]:present world/present age|recent epoch (i.e. the Holocene epoch), 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
八九寺真宵は
現世への存在を許されることになる
She gains citizenship.
She gains proof of residence
—so the story goes.
So for Hachikuji-chan, it's basically
nothing but good things.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 基本的[きほんてき]:fundamental/standard/basic, 尽くめ[ずくめ, づくめ]:entirely/completely/all, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
だから八九寺ちゃんにとっては
基本的にはいいこと尽くめではある
Of course, I'd have to
have her work a bit.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, ちゃあ:if (an action, etc.)|since .../if you are going to ...
もちろん 仕事はしてもらわなくちゃあならないけれども
But if she at least maintains the air pocket,
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business)
しかしエアスポットの管理さえしてくれれば
that will be good enough as
a preventative measure.
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly, 予防策[よぼうさく]:precautionary measures
それだけで十分に予防策にはなる
There you have it.
だそうです
B-But, it's a shrine that
deifies a snake, right?
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
だ... だけど 蛇を祀る神社ですよね?
If you enshrined a snail apparition like
Hachikuji, wouldn't that cause a distortion?
蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 歪み[ひずみ, ゆがみ]:strain/distortion/deformation, 生じる[しょうじる]:to produce/to yield|to result from, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
蝸牛の怪異である八九寺をそこに祀るとなると
また歪みが生じることになるんじゃあ
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
そこが こよみんが考えなしだったというのが
And that is the miracle
that makes it impossible
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, ミラクル:miracle
信じられないくらいのミラクルなんだよね
to believe that you did this
without thinking, Koyomin.
Without that miracle, I never would've thought
about enshrining Hachikuji-chan as a god.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 据える[すえる]:to place (in position)|to install|to settle (upon something)|, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
それがなければ
私も八九寺ちゃんを神に据えようとは思わなかったかもしれない
A snail is a superior version of a snake.
蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 上位[じょうい]:superior (in rank)|higher order (e.g. byte)|host computer (of connected device), 互換[ごかん]:interchange|transposition|compatible (e.g. PC)
蝸牛 は 蛇の上位互換だ
Huh?
No, "superior version" is perhaps stretching
things a little too much.
上位[じょうい]:superior (in rank)|higher order (e.g. byte)|host computer (of connected device), 互換[ごかん]:interchange|transposition|compatible (e.g. PC), 表現[ひょうげん]:expression/presentation|representation, 我田引水[がでんいんすい]:seeking one's own interests/straining (the interpretation or argument) to suit one's own interests/drawing water for one's own field, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
いや 上位互換という表現は我田引水が行き過ぎて
言い過ぎかな
But Koyomin, you've at least
heard of a three-way deadlock?
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 三竦み[さんすくみ]:three-way deadlock, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
だけどこよみん
三竦(すく)みくらいは聞いたことがあるだろう?
A snake, a frog, and a slug...
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 蛙[かえる, かわず]:frog|kajika frog (Buergeria buergeri), 蛞蝓[なめくじ, ナメクジ]:slug
蛇と 蛙と
蛞蝓(なめくじ)が
Slug? Haven't I heard
about that somewhere?
蛞蝓[なめくじ, ナメクジ]:slug
蛞蝓?どこかで聞いたよな
Oh, right.
ああ そうだ
The Slug Tofu.
蛞蝓[なめくじ, ナメクジ]:slug, 豆腐[とうふ]:tofu/bean-curd
蛞蝓豆腐
The fake apparition that
Kaiki used on Sengoku...
施す[ほどこす]:to give (time, money, goods)|to do|to apply (processing, makeup, etc.)||, 偽物[にせもの, にせもん]:spurious article/forgery/counterfeit, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost
貝木が 千石に施していた偽物の怪異...
Right. An apparition effective
against snakes... a slug.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 有効[ゆうこう]:valid/effective|yuko (judo), 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 蛞蝓[なめくじ, ナメクジ]:slug
そう 蛇に有効な怪異 蛞蝓
And, a slug and a snail
are related species.
蛞蝓[なめくじ, ナメクジ]:slug, 蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea, 近縁[きんえん]:close relation (association), 種[しゅ]:kind|(biological) species|(logical) species, 種[たね]:seed (e.g. of a plant)|material (e.g. for an article)|ingredient||
そして 蛞蝓と蝸牛は近縁種だ
Slug                                     Snail
Then, it's not that a snail has
nothing to do with a snake.
蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 関連[かんれん]:relation/connection/relevance, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it
ならば蝸牛は蛇と関連がないどころか
A snail can freeze a snake in place.
蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 抑え込む[おさえこむ]:to shut out one's opponents/to stop the other side from scoring
蝸牛は蛇を 抑え込める
She won't run wild like Sengoku.
暴走[ぼうそう]:acting rashly|runaway (process)|reckless baserunning
千石のように暴走することなく
She won't be swallowed by
the snake like Sengoku.
蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 呑む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
千石のように蛇に呑まれることなく
Instead, she can swallow the snake.
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 呑み込む[のみこむ]:to gulp down|to understand|to engulf||
逆に 蛇を呑み込める
In other words, I'm Mayoi Slug (Namekuji).
ナメクジ:slug
ナメクジ真宵というわけですね
Hachikuji, are you really
all right with that?
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples
八九寺 お前は本当にそれでいいのか?
Yes, I'm fine with it. A god!
That gets me all hyped up!
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
ええ いいですよ 神様
アガるじゃないですか
Hyped up?
アガるって...
Excuse me, I god-ed (kami-mashita)!
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
失礼 神ましたというわけですね
God-ed
Putting it that way makes it
sound like a gag, so stop it.
風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, ギャグ:joke/gag, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
そんな風に言うとギャグみたいになるからやめて
This is really important! Don't
try to make a joke about it!
ギャグ:joke/gag, 引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place, 重大[じゅうだい]:serious/important/significant
ギャグで引き取ろうとしないで
こんな重大なことを
It's way more than just two ranks up!
A tremendous promotion!
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 階級[かいきゅう]:(social) class/rank/grade, 特進[とくしん]:special promotion (in rank or grade), どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
二階級特進どころではない
大出世ですよ
No, you probably don't understand...
たぶん:informing, たぶん:perhaps/probably|generous
いや わかってないってお前 たぶん...
I have a proper understanding.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
わかってますよ ちゃんと
Is that so? Do you properly understand
the responsibilities and meaning,
様になる[ようになる]:to reach the point that/to come to be that/to turn into, 様になる[さまになる, サマになる]:to become good-looking/to start looking appropriate (for something), 行為[こうい]:act/deed/conduct, 責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
そうなのか...?
神様になるという行為の責任や意味
the weight and duties of the
act of becoming a god?
重み[おもみ]:importance/weight/dignity, 役割[やくわり]:part/assigning (allotment of) parts/role, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
重みや役割を
ちゃんとわかっているのか?
No, I don't understand any of
those things. Not at all!
全っ[ぜん]:all/whole|pan-, 然[ぜん]:-like
いえ そういうのは
全っ然わかってないんですけれど
You don't understand?!
わかってないのかよ!
However...
ただし:but/however/provided that
ただし...
I do know that if I do this,
そうなれば
I'll continue to be able to play merrily
with you from now on, Araragi-san.
楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
これからも阿良々木さんと楽しく遊べることだけはわかりますよ
Well, that fulfills one of the conditions.
条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, 満たす[みたす]:to satisfy|to fill (e.g. a cup)|to reach (a certain number)
まあ これで条件のひとつは満たされたということさ
If Hachikuji-chan swallows this talisman,
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, お札[おさつ]:bill/note (currency), お札[おふだ]:type of household amulet or talisman, issued by a Shinto shrine, hung in the house for protection, 呑み込む[のみこむ]:to gulp down|to understand|to engulf||
八九寺ちゃんがこのお札を呑み込めば
it's the birth of a new god
at North Shirahebi Shrine.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 誕生[たんじょう]:birth/creation/formation
北白蛇神社に新たなる神様の誕生というわけだ
If Koyomin wants Hachikuji-chan to
be swallowed up into the darkness,
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 呑む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
こよみんが八九寺ちゃんを "くらやみ" に呑ませたいと言うのならば
well, I'll leave that to your discretion.
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, こよみ:calendar/almanac, 判断[はんだん]:judgment|divination|judgement, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
まあそこはこよみんの判断に任せるけれどね
For me, it's a matter of the means.
手段[しゅだん]:means/way/measure, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
私としては手段の問題だ
Oh, right.
あ... そうだ
Gaen-san.
臥煙さん
What is it, Koyomin?
こよみ:calendar/almanac
なんだい こよみん
Um... About the "darkness"...
くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item
その... "くらやみ" の件なんですけれど
Perhaps we've suffered
a terrible misunderstanding.
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, とんでも:unthinkable/unexpected/outrageous, 勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ひょっとしたら僕達は
とんでもない勘違いをしていたのかもしれません
Ougi Oshino may not be the darkness.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
忍野扇は "くらやみ" ではない
のかもしれません
I know that.
知ってる
Seriously? She wasn't? You're kidding!
マジで? 違ったの? うっそー
I totally thought that was the case,
てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt, 思い込む[おもいこむ]:to be under impression that/to be convinced that/to imagine that
てっきりそうだと思い込んで
and I put tons of foreshadowing of
that nature all over the place!
あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 伏線[ふくせん]:foreshadowing|preparation/precautionary measures, 張る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 張る[ばる]:to be prominently .../to be persistently ..., まくる:to turn up/to roll up (e.g. sleeves)|to do relentlessly
僕 あちこちにそういう伏線を張りまくっちゃったよ
If so, I really wish she hadn't done that.
Please don't deliberately add foreshadowing.
She had a troublesome character trait,
or rather, she was a troublesome character.
Why did you think that in the first place?
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")
そもそも どうしてそう思ったんだい?
That Ougi Oshino was the "darkness."
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, くらやみ:darkness/the dark
忍野扇が "くらやみ" だって
Well, because...
いや だって...
Oh, that was a bad way to ask.
訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||, まずい:poor-quality/shoddy|unskillful, まずい:unappetising/unappetizing|unskillful
ああ 訊きかたがまずかったね
What I want to ask is, at what point did you,
Koyomin, get that idea?
訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||, 段階[だんかい]:grade/level/stage, 段階[きざはし, きだはし]:stairs|stairs at the front of a noh stage, こよみ:calendar/almanac, 発想[はっそう]:idea/conception|expression, 至る[いたる]:to arrive at (e.g. a decision)|to lead to (a place)|to come
私が訊きたいのは
どの段階でこよみんがそんな発想に至ったかということなんだ
There was no specific point.
いつってことはないです
As I watched and listened to her,
I naturally started thinking that way...
言動[げんどう]:speech and conduct/words and deeds, 見聞き[みきき]:information/experience/observation, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, 自然[しぜん]:nature|natural|naturally, 風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold
彼女の言動を見聞きしていたら
自然 そんな風に...
In reality, she was seeking Hachikuji,
and the cases concerning Sengoku and Tadatsuru.
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 正弦[せいげん]:sine
実際あの子 八九寺を探してたりしましたし
千石の件だって 正弦の件だって
No, in the end, it was just a sense I had.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, むしろ:rather/better/instead, むしろ:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 感覚[かんかく]:sense/sensation/feeling, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target
いや 結局のところ僕は
むしろ感覚的に そう思ったのだ
I mean, she felt so shady and
dark... Like darkness itself.
黒々[くろぐろ]:deep black, 雰囲気[ふんいき, ふいんき]:mood|a certain air|air, くらやみ:darkness/the dark
だって 彼女の黒々しい雰囲気は
"くらやみ" そのものだったじゃないか
A shadow that appreciates the rules.
ルール:rule, 重んじる[おもんじる]:to respect/to honor/to honour, 暗黒[あんこく]:darkness
ルールを重んじる 暗黒
A pitch black that reveres balance.
バランス:balance, 奉る[たてまつる, まつる]:to offer|to set someone up in a high position|to do respectfully, 漆黒[しっこく]:jet black
バランスを奉る 漆黒
In the beginning, she herself
probably thought that way, too.
自身[じしん]:by oneself/personally, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first
彼女自身 最初は自分のことをそう思っていたんじゃないのかな
It's certain that even now, she imposes
tasks of that sort on herself.
任[にん]:obligation/duty/charge, 課する[かする]:to levy/to charge/to assess, 確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
今だって そういう任を
彼女が自分に課していることは確かだ
Ougi Oshino is not the "darkness,"
but she does the same thing.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
忍野扇は "くらやみ" でこそないが
しかし "くらやみ" と同じことをしている
She plays the same role.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 役割[やくわり]:part/assigning (allotment of) parts/role, 負う[おう]:to bear|to take responsibility for|to be injured|
同じ役割を負っている
The same role as the "darkness"...
くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 役割[やくわり]:part/assigning (allotment of) parts/role
"くらやみ" と同じ役割...
Let me clear things up just in case—
念[ねん]:sense|desire|attention, 整理[せいり]:sorting|liquidation|retrenchment
念のために整理しておくと
If we leave Hachikuji-chan
in her current condition,
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 放置[ほうち]:leaving as is/leaving alone/leaving to chance
八九寺ちゃんをこの状態のままで放置しておくと
the "darkness" we were worried
might reappear in this town
またぞろ:(yet) again, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 生じる[しょうじる]:to produce/to yield|to result from, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, くらやみ:darkness/the dark
またぞろこの町に生じるかもしれないと
さっきまで心配していた "くらやみ" は
will be the true "darkness".
掛け値[かけね]:inflated price (assigned in anticipation of being haggled down)/overcharging|exaggeration, くらやみ:darkness/the dark
掛け値なく本当の "くらやみ" だ
On the other hand, if we set up and enshrine
Hachikuji-chan as the god of North Shirahebi Shrine,
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 仮[け]:lacking substance and existing in name only/something without substance, 仮[かり]:temporary|fictitious|hypothetical, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 仕立て上げる[したてあげる]:to make out to be/to set someone up (as)/to prepare (e.g. someone for a role)
対して 仮に八九寺ちゃんを北白蛇神社の神様に仕立て上げ
it's possible that Hachikuji-chan
will be attacked
祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, やっぱり:too/also|still, 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
祀り上げたところで
やっぱり八九寺ちゃんを襲うかもしれないのが
by Ougi Oshino, who performs the same
role as the "darkness."
くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 役割[やくわり]:part/assigning (allotment of) parts/role, 負う[おう]:to bear|to take responsibility for|to be injured|, 野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan
"くらやみ" と同じ役割を負う 忍野扇なんだ
After we enshrine... attacked?
祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit
祀り上げたところで... 襲う?
Well, that's why I said there were two
minimum requirements, didn't I?
最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|, 条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term
いや だから最低条件はふたつあると言っただろう
Merely enshrining Hachikuji-chan
as a god is not enough.
寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
八九寺ちゃんを神に祀り上げるだけじゃあ
足りないんだ
If we don't exterminate Ougi Oshino,
the story doesn't come to a conclusion.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., まったく:really/truly|indeed, まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order
忍野扇を退治しないと
話はまったくまとまらない
Exterminate, exterminate...
You keep repeating that.
退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
退治 退治って...
そう繰り返しますけれど
But can you stop that?
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
それ やめてもらっていいですか
When you say exterminate, it's as
if Ougi-chan was an apparition.
退治[たいじ]:extermination (e.g. of pests, demons, bandits)|making someone renounce worldly desires in order to concentrate on Buddha's teachings|curing illness, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
退治なんていう言いかたをしたら
まるで扇ちゃんが 怪異みたいじゃないですか
That's right.
そうだよ
She is an ordinary...
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train
彼女は普通の...
...monster.
化物[ばけもの, ばけもん]:goblin/apparition/monster
化物だ